Guide to the Loren R. Mosher Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
- Publications, Series 2; 6 box(es)
  - Journal articles (as numbered by LRM):
    - "Families with Identical Twins Discordant for Schizophrenia: Some Relationships between Identification, Thinking Styles, Psychopathology and Dominance-Submissiveness," by Mosher, Pollin, and Stabenau, British Journal of Psychiatry, 118 (1971) 29-42. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Publication #22 "Identical Twins Discordant for Schizophrenia: Neurological Findings," by Mosher, Pollin, and Stabenau, Arch Gen Psychiat 24 (May 1971). (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Publication #23: "Symposium 27: Schizoidness in the non-schizophrenic co-twins of schizophrenics," by Mosher, Stabenau, and Pollin, Excerpta Medica International Congress Series No. 274. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Publication #24: "Etiological Implications of Studies of Identical Twins Discordant for Schizophrenia," Orthomolecular Psychiatry 1, no. 1 (First Quarter, 1972). (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Publication #25: "Recent Trends in Psychological Treatment of Schizophrenia," The American Journal of Psychoanalysis XXXII, no. 1. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Publication #26: "A Research Design for Evaluating a Psychosocial Treatment of Schizophrenia," Hospital and Community Psychiatry 23, no. 8 (August 1972). (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Publication #27: "Cognitive Style, Schizophrenia, and the Family: Methodological Implications of Contextual Effects" by Mosher, Wild, Valcov, and Feinstein, Family Process 11, no. 2 (June 1972). (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Publication #31: "Characteristics of Nonprofessionals Serving as Primary Therapists for Acute Schizophrenics," by Mosher, Reifman, and Menn, Hospital and Community Psychiatry 24 (6) (1973), 391-396. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Publication #33: "Psychiatric Heretics and the Extra-Medical Treatment of Schizophrenia" in Strategic Intervention in Schizophrenia: Current Developments in Treatment, edited by Cancro, Fox, and Shapiro (New York: Behavioral Publications, 1974), 279-302. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Publication #34: "The Cost of Schizophrenia," by Gunderson and Mosher, American Journal of Psychiatry 132(9) (September 1975), 901-906. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Publication #40: "Soteria: Evaluation of a Home-based Treatment for Schizophrenia," by Mosher, Menn, and Matthews, Amer. J. Orthopsychiatry, 45(3) (April 1975). (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - [Publication # 42?] "The Soteria Project. An Alternative to Hospitalization for Schizophrenics: Some Clinical Aspects," by Menn and Mosher Schizophrenia 75, edited by Jarl Jorstad and Endre Ugelstand (Oslo, Norway: Universitetsforlaget, 1976), 347-372. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Publication #43: "Family Therapy for Schizophrenia: Recent Trends" in Treatment of Schizophrenia: Progress and Prospect, edited by West and Flinn (Grune & Stratton, Inc., 1976). (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Publication #44: "Implications of Family Studies for the Treatment of Schizophrenia" Irish Medical Journal 69 (17) (1976), 456-463. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Publication #45 "Dinosaur or Astronaut? One Year Followup Data from the Soteria Project" by Mosher and Menn, in "A Symposium: Followup Studies of Community Care," edited by M. Greenblatt and R. D. Budson, American Journal of Psychiatry 133(8) (1976), 919-920. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Publication #46: "Being With Madness: Personality Characteristics of Three Treatment Staffs," by Hirschfield, Matthews, Mosher, and Menn, Hospital Community Psychiatry 28, no. 4 (April 1977). (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Publication #47 "Evaluation of Community Mental Health Services," Martin Katz (Moderator); Societal Barriers to Learning: the Community Psychiatry Example -- Loren R. Mosher. Chapter 3 in A Critical Appraisal of Community Psychiatry, edited by G. Serban (New York: John Wiley and Sons, Inc, 1977), 145-161. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Publication #48: "Lowered Barriers in the Community: The Soteria Model," by Mosher and Menn, in Alternative to Mental Hospital Treatment, edited by Stern and Test (NY: Plenum Press, 1978). (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Publication #51 "Can Diagnosis be Nonpejorative?" in The Nature of Schizophrenia, edited by Wynne (John Wiley & Sons, Inc., 1978). (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - [no label]: "Community Residential Treatment for Schizophrenia: Two-Year Follow-Up," by Mosher and Menn, Hospital and Community Psychiatry, 29, no. 11 (Nov. 1978). (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - [Publication #54]: "The Surrogate 'Family,' an Alternative to Hospitalization" by Mosher and Menn, in Schizophrenia: Science and Practice, edited by J.C. Shershow (Cambridge, Massachusetts: Harvard University Press, 1978), 223-239. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - [Publication #55]: "A Non-Neuroleptic Treatment for Schizophrenia: Analysis of the Two-Year Postdischarge Risk of Relapse," by Matthews, Roper, Mosher, and Menn, Schizophrenia Bulletin 5, no. 2, (1979). (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - [Publication #56]: "Research on the Psychosocial Treatment of Schizophrenia: A Summary Report," by Mosher and Keith, American Journal of Psychiatry 136 no. 5 (May 1979). Includes correspondence re: use of article. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Publication #57: "Soteria: An Alternative to Hospitalization for Schizophrenia," by Mosher and Menn, New Directions for Mental Health Services 1 (1979). (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Publication #59: "Group, Family, Milieu, and Community Support Systems Treatment for Schizophrenia," by Mosher and Gunderson, in The Schizophrenic Syndrome, edited by L. Bellak (Basic Books, 1979), 399-451. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Publication #60: "Comparison of Two Treatment Environments for Schizophrenia," by Wendt, Mosher, Matthews, and Menn, in Principles and Practices of Milieu Theory, edited by Gunderson, Will, Mosher (New York: Jason Aronson Pub., 1983). Includes draft. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - [no label]: "Recent Research Trends in Schizophrenia," in Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, 3rd, ed. A. M. Friedman, H. I. Kaplan, and B.J. Sadock (Baltimore: The Williams and Wilkins Co., in press [in 1978]) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - [no label]: "Drugs and Psychosocial Treatment: Editors' Introduction," by Mosher and Meltzer, Schizophrenia Bulletin 6, no. 1 (1980). (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - [no label]: "Diagnosis of Schizophrenia...," correspondence related to. Article not included (1982 letter from Murray Morphy; 1983 letter from Joan Oliver). (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Publication #66: "Italy's Revolutionary Mental Health Law: An Assessment," American Journal of Psychiatry 139:2 (February 1982). (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - [no label]: "A Psychosocial Approach to the Returning Schizophrenic," The Schizophrenic Outpatient: A Clinical Information Service 1, no.1 (1982). (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Publication #67 "Radical Deinstitutionalization: the Italian Experience," Int. J. Ment. Health 11, no. 4 (M. E. Sharpe, Inc. 1983), 129-136. Includes related correspondence and other materials. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Publication #68: "Recent Developments in the Care, Treatment, and Rehabilitation of the Chronic Mentally Ill in Italy," Hospital and Community Psychiatry 34, no. 10 (October 1983). (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Publication #69: "Scientific Evidence and System Change: The Soteria Experience" by Mosher and Menn, in Psychosocial Interventions in Schizophrenia, edited by H. Steirlin et. al. (Heidelberg: Springer-Verlag, 1983), 93-108. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - [Publication # 71]: "Crossing Place: A Residential Model for Crisis Intervention," by Wolff, Matthews, Kalibat, and Mosher, Hospital and Community Psychiatry 35, no. 1 (Jan. 1984). (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Publication #72: "Un' Alternativa All'ospedalizzazione Nella Schizofrenia: L'Esperienza Soteria," by Mosher and Menn, in Le Psicosi Schizofreniche. Dalla Ricerca alla Pratica Clinica, a cura di C. Faccinani, R. Fiorio, G. Mignolli e M. Tansella (Bologna: Patr"00F3"n, 1984.) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Publication #73: "Alternatives to Psychiatric Hospitalization: Why Has Research Failed to be Translated into Practice?," The New England Journal of Medicine 309 (December 22, 1983). Includes related correspondence and other materials. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - [Publication # 74]: "Milieu Therapy in the 1980s: A Comparison of Two Residential Alternatives to Hospitalization," by Mosher, Kresky-Wolff, Matthews, and Menn, Bull Menninger Clin. 50(3) (1986),257-268. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Publication #75: Commentary [on essay by Julian P. Leff], Integrative Psychiatry: An International Journal for the Synthesis of Medicine and Psychiatry 3, no. 2 (June 1985). (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Publication #76: "The Current Status of the Community Support Program: A Personal Assessment," Psychosocial Rehabilitation Journal 9, no. 3 (January, 1986). (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Publication#77 "Training Psychiatrists in the Community: A Report of the Italian Experience," by Burti and Mosher, Am. J. Psychiatry 143:12 (December 1986). (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Publication #78 "Community Residential Treatment: Alternatives to Hospitalization," in A Clinical Guide for the Treatment of Schizophrenia, by A. Bellack (N. Y.: Plenum Press, 1989). (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Publication #79: "The Soteria Project: New Outcome Data," by Mosher, Vallone, and Menn, in New Trends in Schizophrenia, edited by Migone, Martini, & Volterra, (Caserta: Edito Dalla Fondazione [Centro Praxis] 1989), 113-330. Includes Italian version. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Publication #80: "On Being Therapeutic Without Doing Therapy," Congresso Nazionale della Societa Italiana di Riabilitazione Psicosociale (S. I. R. P.). Verona, 29-30 ottobre 1988. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Publication #81 "Relationships in Rehabilitations: When Technology Fails," by Mosher and Burti, Psychosocial Rehabilitation Journal 15, no. 4 (April 1992). Includes a related correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Publication #82 "Soteria: A Therapeutic Community for Psychotic Persons," International Journal of Therapeutic Communities 12, no. 1 (1991). (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Publication #83: "An Anti-Psychiatrist's Contribution to Contemporary Psychiatry: A Personal Memoir," International Journal of Therapeutic Communities 12, no. 1 (1991). (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Publication #85: "The Social Environmental Treatment of Psychosis: Critical Ingredients," in Psychotherapy of Schizophrenia: Facilitating and Obstructive Factors, edited by A. Werbart and J. Cullberg, (Oslo: Scandinavian University Press, 1992), 254-260. Multiple versions. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Publication #86: "Expanding Forced Treatment: Where Will It All End?" (response to Swartz and Siebert in "Should it be Easier to Commit People Involuntarily to Treatment?") in Controversial Issues in Mental Health (New York: Allyn and Bacon, 1994). (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Publication #87: "The Soteria Project: The First-Generation American Alternatives to Psychiatric Hospitalization" in Alternatives to the Hospital For Acute Psychiatric Treatment, edited by Richard Warner (1995). Includes copies of handout Community Mental Health Relational Principles. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Publication #88: "Soteria: A Therapeutic Community for Psychotic Persons" (1996). (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Publication #89: "Residential Alternatives to Hospitalization for Patients with Severe and Persistent Mental Illness: Should Patients With Comorbid Substance Abuse be Excluded?" by Herrell, Mosher et. al, The Journal of Mental Health Administration 23:3 (Summer 1996). (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Publication #90: "The Treatment of Acute Psychosis Without Neuroleptics: Six-Week Psychopathology Outcome Data from the Soteria Project," International Journal of Social Psychiatry 41, no. 3 (1995). Includes a related correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Publication #91: "Mapping an Understanding of Madness." Consumer Connection 4, no. 1 (1995). (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Publication #92 "Family Therapy," by Mosher and Schreiber, Psychiatry 2, ch. 75 (1997). Includes a related correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Publication #93: "Psych and Rehabilitation: Rapprochement," by Mosher/VanDevanter, presented at Second Annual Meeting of the Italian Society for Psychological Rehabilitation, 1990. Includes correspondence and related materials. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Publication #94: "Organizing a User Friendly Community Mental Health System: Program Values and Clinical Principles" for "Die Psychiatric von Morgen im Kanton Zurich" (1993). Includes a related correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Publication #95: "Randomized Trial of General Hospital and Residential Alternative Care for Patients with Severe and Persistent Mental Illness," by Fenton, Mosher, et. al., The American Journal of Psychiatry 155:4 (April 1998). (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Publication #96: "Soteria and Other Alternatives to Acute Psychiatric Hospitalization: A Personal and Professional Review," The Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease 187, no. 3 (1999). Includes related correspondence and materials. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Swimming Upriver," forward to book by Lars Martensson. Includes correspondence, drafts and other related materials. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "The Ethics of Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT)," op-ed by Mosher and David Cohen, Virtual Mentor: Ethics Journal of the American Medical Association (October 2003). Includes related materials. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "Rethinking the Mental Illness Industry," by Mosher and Mary Boyle (2003). Includes notes and related newsclipping. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Publication #97: "The Soteria Affect," by Bola and Mosher (1997-1999). Includes drafts and correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Publication #99: "The Soteria Project: Twenty five years of swimming upriver," by Mosher and Bola, Complexity and Change 9, no. 1 (June 2000). (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Publication #100 "Treating Madness Without Hospitals: Soteria and Its Successors" in The Handbook of Humanistic Psychology, edited Schneider, Bugental, and Pierson (Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage, 2001). (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Publication #101: "Soteria-California and its Successors: Therapeutic ingredients," in Wie wirkt Soteria?-ein atypische Psychosenbehandlung kritisch durchleuchtet, edited by Ciompi and Hoffman (New York and Bonn: Huber, 2001). Includes related correspondence and other materials. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Publication #102: Includes only related correspondence and other materials. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Publication #103 "Application of Soteria Therapeutic Principles to Community Psychiatric Care" (2001). Includes related correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Publication #104 -- Prosky Chap: "Pharmland" Pig Pharma: Psychiatric Agenda Setting by Drug Companies (email/letter correspondence; copy of "Pig Pharma: Psychiatric Agenda Setting by Drug Companies," by Beder, Gosden, and Mosher; in Family Therapy and Psychopharmacology, edited by Prosky and Keith. Final title of chapter is apparently "Biopsychiatric Ideology as an impediment to Consumerism." Includes related material and correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Publication #112: "Attitudes, values, and beliefs of mental health workers," by Burti and Mosher, in Epidemiologia E Psichiatria Sociale 12, no. 4, 227-232. Includes correspondence and other related materials. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Publication #114: "Treatment of newly diagnosed psychosis without anti-psychotic drugs: The Soteria project," by Bola, Mosher, and Cohen, in Mental Disorders in the Social Environment: Critical Perspectives, edited by Stuart A. Kirk (New York: Columbia University Press, 2003). Includes correspondence and related materials. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Unnumbered articles, alphabetical:
    - "At Issue: Predicting Drug-Free Treatment Response in Acute Psychosis from the Soteria Project," Schizophrenia Bulletin, Vol. 28, No. 4, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "The Biopsychiatric Model of 'Mental Illness': A Critical Bibliography," The Rights Tenet, Spring 2001 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - "Crisis residential care for patients with serious mental illness," from Psychosis: Psychological Approaches and their Effectiveness (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Dabeisein: Das Manual zur Praxis in der Soteria, Psychiatrie Verlag, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Models of Madness, photocopies of several chapters by Mosher (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - "Schizophrenia," Today's Education, March 1971 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "Soteria-California and its American Successors: Therapeutic Ingredients," Ethnical Human Psychology and Psychiatry, Vol. 6, Number 1, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "Treatment of Acute Psychosis without Neuroleptics: Two-Year Outcomes from the Soteria Project," Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, Vol. 191, No. 4 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Books:
    - Community Mental Health, Principles and Practice by Loren R. Mosher and Lorenzo Burti. W. W. Norton 1989. And 8 foreign translations (Box 5)
    - Psychotherapy of Schizophrenia. Edited by John G. Gunderson and Loren R. Mosher, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Issues and Controversies in the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenia. Edited by John G. Gunderson and Loren R. Mosher, 1994 paperback edition (Box 6)
    - Models of Madness; Psychological, Social and Biological Approaches to Schizophrenia. Edited by John Read, Loren R. Mosher and Richard P. Bentall, 2004. Hardcover and paperback copies (Box 6)
  - Books with articles by Loren R. Mosher:
    - Community Care and Psychiatric Rehabilitation for Persons with Serious Mental Illness, edited by Jaap van Weeghel, 2002 (Box 6)
    - Towards a Whole Society; Collected Papers on Aspects of Mental Health, edited by Ruth Terrington, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Psychosocial Approaches to Deeply Disturbed Persons, edited by Peter R. Breggin and E. Mark Stern [volume 9, numbers 3 and 4, 1996 of the Psychotherapy Patient, a journal of attribute-focused practice] (Box 6)
    - R. D. Laing, Contemporary Perspectives, edited by Salman Raschid, 2005. (Box 6)
    - Coming off Psychiatric Drugs, edited by Peter Lehmann, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Mental Disorders in the Social Environment, Critical Perspectives, edited by Stuart A. Kirk, 2005 (Box 6)